Alexander Chermenin

I began programming when I was about 8 years old. Started from small - wrote my first programs using long-forgotten language G-BASIC, later it was QuickBasic, and then Delphi with all charms of visual programming. Year by year, time passed, technologies were changing (there was a time when I was writing in C++, C+, Ruby, Scala, Haskell, PHP, and more and more Java), and this isn't all. Today I'm working with a lot of tools for Big Data processing (and taking a part in work on a couple of them).

Technical Skills

Likes: java scala spring hadoop apache-spark hive bigdata apache-flink

Experience

Big Data Engineer - EPAM Systems

Sep 2016 → Current

java, scala, hadoop, mapreduce, hive, apache-spark, apache-flink

- Big Data course (including Hadoop, Hive, Spark and auxiliary things such as Oozie, Flume, HBase, Cassandra, etc.)
- · contributing to Apache Flink open-source project
- implementing a competition platform to compare algorithms for identifying of rare diseases (using Apache Spark)
- processing for different kinds of logs using Logstash, Beats, Elasticsearch and Kibana

Principal Software Developer - Sberbank Technology

Jul 2015 → Sep 2016

java, spring, xslt, xml, xpression, xforms, tomcat, websphere, git, hadoop, apache-spark, scala, hive, bigdata

- web forms development using IBM Forms
- development of web services using Java with (and without) Spring
- big data processing using Java and Scala with Hadoop, Spark and Hive

Middle Java Developer - DartlT

 $\textit{Mar 2015} \rightarrow \textit{Jun 2015}$

java, angularjs, spring, aop, oracle, weblogic, maven, intellij-idea, git, mercurial, jpa, hibernate, rest, servlets, mongodb

- development of web interfaces using AngularJS
- development of web services using Java with (and without) Spring and Hibernate
- deployment and support Apache Tomcat
- support for database Oracle

Java Developer – Pro IT

Sep 2014 → Mar 2015

java, angularis, spring, aop, oracle, weblogic, maven, intellij-idea, git, mercurial, jpa, hibernate, rest, servlets, mongodb

- · development of web interfaces using AngularJS
- development of web services using Java EE with Spring and Hibernate
- deployment and support Oracle WebLogic
- support for database Oracle

PHP / Java Developer - Prognoz

Jul 2013 → Sep 2014

php, java, gwt, javascript, apache, tomcat, servlets, rest, objective-c, oracle, sql-server, websphere, angularjs, maven, intellijidea, git, mercurial, svn, jpa, spring, hibernate

- web application development using Java and GWT
- development of web interfaces using AngularJS
- development of web services using Java EE with Spring and Hibernate
- · development of web applications using PHP
- deployment and support Apache HTTP Server, Apache Tomcat
- deployment and support GlassFish Server
- deployment and support Oracle WebLogic
- support for database Oracle

Junior PHP / Java Developer – Prognoz

Jun 2010 → Jul 2012

php, java, gwt, javascript, apache, tomcat, servlets, rest, objective-c, oracle, sql-server, websphere

- development of information-analytical systems and decision support systems using its own analytical complex Prognoz Platform and through third-party programming systems (Microsoft Visual Studio, XCode)
- development of monitoring services using Microsoft Visual Studio (C#)
- development of web interfaces using ASP.NET technology
- development of mobile applications for iPad using XCode (Objective-C)
- deployment and support of database Microsoft SQL Server 2008 R2, Oracle 11g
- installation and configuration of OS Red Hat, AIX
- · deployment of IBM WebSphere and IBM InfoSphere MDM for PIM

Education

Engineer at specialty information system and technologies – Perm State Agricultural Academy $2008 \rightarrow 2015$ pascal, freepascal, delphi, java, php, sql-server, active-directory, windows, windows-server-2008, autocad, c++, networking, security, gis, electronics

Projects & Interests

Sberbank Open Data Dashboard – https://github.com/chermenin/sberbank-opendata docker, ansible, elasticsearch, vagrant, kibana, logstash, apache-kafka

Sep 2017 → Current

It is a sample to show how to process some data using Filebeat and Logstash and how to visualize that to get some information. The open data were downloaded from a Sberbank site. Also, Vagrant and Ansible are used for deploying and testing.

flink-siddhi – https://github.com/chermenin/flink-siddhi java, scala, bigdata, apache-flink, flink-cep, cep

Jul 2017 → Current

A CEP library for Flink to run Siddhi within Apache Flink streaming application

Apache Flink – https://github.com/chermenin/flink java, scala, bigdata, apache-flink

Aug 2016 → Current

Apache Flink is an open source stream processing framework with powerful stream- and batch-processing capabilities.

FreelanceHunt Messenger – https://bitbucket.org/chermenin/flh-messenger java, javafx, multithreading, dto, web-services

Nov 2014 → Current

Client for FreelanceHunt web site using API.

Author and developer

Simple Java XML Server – https://bitbucket.org/chermenin/xml-server java, groovy, xml, jetty

Nov 2014 → Current

This is implementation of a simple server for education.

Author and developer

Sija Framework – https://github.com/chermenin/sija php, json, activerecord, rest

Jul 2014 \rightarrow Current

Sija is an open source software implementation of some guidelines and small framework written in PHP to help quickly and easily create a simple REST-services and web applications using JSON API.

Author and developer

Apps & Software

Sija Framework – http://chermenin.github.io/sija/php, json, activerecord, rest

Jan 2015

Sija is an open source software implementation of some guidelines and small framework written in PHP to help quickly and easily create a simple REST-services and web applications.

Author and developer

Battery Mark for OS X – https://itunes.apple.com/ru/app/battery-mark/id1022826698 objective-c, core-plot, osx, xcode

Aug 2013

Battery mark is a great tool that allows you to evaluate overall status of a power system in your laptop and test it in the most extreme conditions.

Main features: - execution of quick testing to show battery ability during a time of discharge by 4-6% - full testing of laptop power system with displaying of a graph of discharge - the ability to run calculating process to make a full load of each processor core - simulation of a load on the disk subsystem, including reading and writing data - calculation of the final mark to compare laptops or batteries - making a report for use or research later

Author and developer

Imtec Battery Mark – http://chermenin.ru/bmark/delphi, acpi, wmi

Aug 2009

Imtec Battery Mark is a powerful software solution that tests the laptop battery and helps you determine whether it needs to be replaced or not.

Author and developer

Tools

First Computer: CCM Partner 01.01, Subor SB225-B, IBM PC-compatible (Celeron 500 / 32Mb / 9Gb / 4Mb 3D)

Favorite Editor: IntelliJ IDEA, Atom, nano, vim